[CHIME]
[APPLAUSE]
JESSE SADLER: Thank you.
All right, so my
name's Jesse Sadler.
I am a historian.
I teach at Loyola
Marymount University.
And so even though I am
talking about vctrs today,
what I normally do--
and just quickly,
the slides are online
and I'll have a link at the end.
But what I normally
do is I study history.
I am a historian.
I'm interested in merchant
networks and merchant families
in the 16th and 17th century.
And I'm particularly
interested in inheritance
and what inheritance shows
about how people interacted
with each other and how families
interacted with each other.
And so that leads
me to doing math.
Specifically, in
terms of doing math
with non-decimal currencies.
So these are currencies like
here, this is Flemish pounds.
But basically, currencies
that are in pounds, shillings,
and pence.
And this is a problem
because we don't
learn how to do non-decimal
arithmetic anymore.
And computers are obviously
based on decimal arithmetic.
And so you can't just plug
these numbers into a computer
and do an analysis on
them, it doesn't really
work that way, unfortunately.
So what exactly is
the problem space?
The problem space is that
with non-decimal currencies,
you have to do something called
compound unit arithmetic,
right?
So you have to add up
the separate columns,
and then divide by the
base of that column.
And then you can
get your answer.
So in other words,
we have a number
of different problems here.
We have three separate units
that make up one value.
Those units do not
have decimal bases.
So therefore, we need to use
this compound unit arithmetic.
And finally to make things even
worse, the units can differ.
So the normal, sort of most-used
units in historical occurrences
is to have 20
shillings in a pound,
and 12 pence in a shilling.
But they could change, right?
So you guys didn't know you were
getting so much history today.
JJ in the keynote,
already talked
about history of corporations.
This is what he
is talking about.
I'll have some stuff
about corporate-- well,
some ideas about corporations.
So there is a problem and
you can't just plug this in.
However, programming languages
like R are very flexible.
And so you can use them
to do this essentially
compound arithmetic yourself.
So what we want to do in
a situation like this,
is we want to be able to take
these totals, which are just
added up, right, and
then normalize them, do
the compound unit
arithmetic in order
to get the answer that we want.
And so you can make a,
what I'm calling here,
a normalize() function,
which basically
takes a vector of
length three, the amount
of units that we have,
and then normalizes
them using remainder
division, essentially.
And then brings
them all together.
OK.
So this is great.
We have a normalize() function.
We're ready to go.
We've got something.
We can even create an S3 class.
And S3 classes-- who here
has built their own S3
classes before?
All right, a number
of you, right?
S3 classes are great because
they're really easy to make,
right?
I just built an S3 class, right?
The key here is the
structure() part, right?
And so this is a class that
has a value into it, x.
And then it has, I
called the class "lsd",
which is the Latin terminology
for pounds, shillings,
and pence.
And then I've added
a bases attributes
so that we can know what
the bases of the shillings
and pence units are.
All right, and so
I can just do this.
And I can create something and
it doesn't have a nice printing
method or anything right now.
But I've created an S3 class.
OK, so great.
I've created S3 class.
Now I'm going to sit
down and figure out,
what am I going to do with this?
What else do I need to do?
Well, right now, I can only
have one value at a time.
So maybe I need to have
multiple values so I
should use a list or something.
And then I need to change
the normalization method.
OK, no problem.
All right, so what
else do I need to do?
OK, at this point, it
gets really confusing
because you have to
implement all these methods.
And it's not really
clear how exactly
you're going to
do them, and what
methods you have to
implement, and why
you need to do them and so on.
And so basically, I went through
this and I implemented some
methods and some I didn't.
And then I talked to
Hadley Wickham and he said,
no, what you should do is
that you should use vctrs.
And so vctrs is a
package that gives you
a path to implementing all
of those different methods
to actually creating
your own S3
class without having
to know everything
there is to know about
the different S3 classes.
So the goals of
the vctrs package
are fairly simple in
some ways, but very deep.
It's about type stability
and size stability.
And Hadley talked about this
at the last RStudio conference.
But I am going to focus on
this last aspect of building S3
classes.
So what do you get by
using this vctrs package?
Well, as I said before,
you get a clear path.
But you also get
consistency with base R.
It's just an S3
class and so there's
no reason why your
users would need to know
that it's based on vctrs.
And then finally,
it is integrated
and continuing to be
integrated into the Tidyverse.
OK, so what I want
to do in this talk,
and for the rest of
the talk basically,
is talk about why you might
want to create your own S3
class through this example
of non-decimal currencies.
Why you should use vctrs.
And to point you to some
things of how you can do it.
And I don't have enough
time to go through and do
all of a tutorial on this and
show all the different steps.
And so what I've done, is I've
created a package that I'm
calling debvctrs,
which is a simplified
version of the
package where I've
done more of this, in debkeepr.
And you see the URLs there.
And what the debvctrs
package is, is it
provides a tutorial
of a step-by-step way
to get through this.
And I will go through
some of these steps now.
And so just as a side,
the image that you see
there is a trademark of an
individual who would use that.
So again, more history stuff.
OK, so there's basically
six different steps
to creating a S3
class with vctrs.
Again, I'm not going to
go through all these.
I'm going to concentrate on the
first half-- the first three.
And I won't go into
the last three,
but I will talk about them.
You'll see how they are
when they're implemented.
And if you're creating a class
that's based on double vectors,
you only have to do four of these.
Two of these steps
you get for free.
And so just to give you an
idea, so debvctrs is a package
and it's tested and
it has everything.
But the way that the scripts
are organized is to follow this.
And then within the
scripts, there's
a lot of different comments
on how to do these things.
So I definitely recommend
that you go and look at this.
It's on GitHub and you
see that you URL there.
OK, so let's go through
some of these choices
that I made with
debkeepr / debvctrs.
And so just as a
reminder, right,
to go back to our
problem space, we
have to deal with these
issues of compound unit
arithmetic of representing
a single value with three
different numbers.
So in designing this, I
thought about different things.
So one, I didn't want to
just decimalize everything.
I wanted to maintain the
structure of the numbers.
I wanted to keep track of
the bases of the shillings
and pence because
they could differ.
And I wanted to make sure
that if two values had
different bases,
that they couldn't
be combined in any way.
But at the same time, I did want
to create a decimalized class
that I could use as a fallback.
And this would have the same
basic attributes of a bases
attribute that you
could follow what
the different bases of the
pounds and shillings are.
But in addition, it would
have an attribute on the unit.
So it would be a
decimalized unit
of the pounds unit, or the
shillings unit, or the pence
unit, right?
And different units
can come together
because they can be
the same currency,
but there needs to be a
way in which that's done.
And so I'm calling
these classes deb_lsd,
deb is short for double
entry bookkeeping,
which is where you find
all these different values.
And then deb_decimal.
So again, I'm not
going to go into this.
But this just gives
you an idea of this--
these are the steps within
the first major step
of creating the vector.
And so it's broken down here.
And I'll just give
you this slide,
which is a simplified version
of the creation of the class.
This doesn't have any
checks or anything,
but you can see here
the different arguments
that we have on the left.
The different vectors that
can be put in for pounds,
shillings, and pence.
And then on the right
just the single one.
And then the attributes
of each class.
And then here, we have
the actual creation.
And so with the
deb_lsd, when we want
to keep these
tripartite structures,
I'm going to use a
record-style vector.
And so this is
essentially a list that
has vectors of equal length.
And so that gives us
a basis from which
we can have this
different structure--
this tripartite structure.
On the right, it's just
essentially, again,
a double vector.
So here, we have now--
I'm skipping some steps, right?
But this is what it looks like
if we implement our class.
And so we can start
here on the left.
We have now a function
where we can create a class.
And so we have
different things that we
can add into the pound's
values, the shillings values,
the pence values.
And here we're going to take
our standard basis of 12 and 20.
And on the right is
an equivalent vector
that is a decimalized.
And here we have the printing
methods that I've chosen.
So again, these are things
that you can create.
So here, I've chosen to
include the base attributes
and the unit attributes
so it's very clear.
And both work
natively with tibble.
The record-style vectors
are not fully integrated,
but they're getting there.
So the last thing I
want to talk about here
that I have time to
talk about is the issue
of casting and
coercion, which is
really at the heart of what is
happening as you are creating
your vectors, your classes,
and want them to interact
with other different classes.
So the workflow is
fairly simple simple.
You have a boilerplate that you're
going to use on each time.
And this is the same for
casting and coercion,
where you define the
method for the class.
And then you give
a default, then
you do the methods
within the class.
And then the methods with
any compatible classes
that you decide to choose.
So what coercion
and casting do is
they are kind of two
sides of the same coin.
Coercion looks
for and determines
what the common type is with
this function, vec_ptype2().
While casting does the
actual transformation.
And so things like
comparison between classes
are made possible
by implementing
both of these things.
So again, I don't have a
chance to go through all this,
but coercion is really
about design choices.
There's not necessarily
that much code that
goes into something like this.
And so in this
instance, with debvctrs
I decided to have a double
goes to deb_decimal,
which would then
go to a deb_lsd.
So if you had these three
types in combined function
then you would get a deb_lsd.
Casting is a little
bit more interesting
because this is where we
have the programmatic logic
of the actual transformation.
And one reason why I
think that debvctrs
is an interesting
example of this
is because I have two
different kinds of vectors.
And so you have to think
about how you can combine them
in different ways.
And so here, again, the
code is not necessarily
super easy to read, but
this is taking a deb_decimal
and then converting it to
this tripartite structure.
And essentially, what I'm
doing is taking simple ifelse
statement, what is the unit.
And then from that
unit, placing it
where it should be in a call
to create a deb_lsd vector.
And then finally,
normalizing it so
that we get a normalized
value so that we've done
the compound unit arithmetic.
OK, so how do we
put it all together?
So this is essentially
the end point.
Here, I'm just showing
that what you can get.
So we can combine deb_lsd,
deb_decimal, and double
and we get deb_lsd.
We can compare different
types, so 3,255 pence
is less than 15 pounds.
And again, if you
go on, you can do
arithmetic, including
arithmetic with different types.
So what I want to say
is, that you can create
your own S3 three vectors.
You can extend the capabilities
of R to fix your own--
fit your own needs.
And that vctrs provides this
clear developmental path
that enables you to do this.
Thank you.
[APPLAUSE]
HOST: Thank you
very much, Jesse.
That was fantastic.
We have a couple of questions.
If you still want to
sneak one in, please do.
There's a question about whether
you can comment on your choice
between--
you mentioned explicitly
S3 and vectors.
Did you consider
R6 classes?
And how did that factor
into your decision making?
So I looked at
it a little bit,
but mostly I was
sort of interested
in the simplicity of S3.
And like I said, I basically
wrote the entire package
with S3 based on lists.
And then I talked to Hadley, and
then I had like a month of work
to do.
[LAUGHTER]
So the second
question is, once you
had your data in
vctrs format, what
did you have to do
additionally to make
it compatible with Tidyverse?
So like I said,
especially if your vector
is based on a double,
then it pretty much
works right out of the package.
Right now, with
record-style vectors,
there are some things like
mutate() that don't quite work.
But I know that RStudio
is working on that.
But there, you can
just go back to base R
things that work just fine.
And hopefully, soon that
will also get figured out.
And the final question,
what was the process--
what was your
original data format?
I mean, how do you go from
paper records into vectors?
Yeah, so it's fun
thinking about the questions
of big data, because I have
to create all of my own data.
And it's also funny
to think about it
in terms of reproducible data.
Oh, don't change the data.
And it's like, well, wait.
I created it.
I can change it if I want to.
But basically, I
take these numbers,
I take these documents,
and I input them
by hand trying to figure
out what the numbers are.
And do it in a
spreadsheet program,
and then export it CSV.
And there is a function in
debkeepr, but not in debvctrs
that will take that and
create deb_lsd columns
from those three
different columns.
Thank you very much.
Thank you.
[APPLAUSE]
[CHIME]